Guide to the Douglas MacKinnon Papers, 1917-1982 RL.00834
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Douglas MacKinnon papers
1917-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
MacKinnon, Douglas, 1903-1984
RL.00834
14 Linear Feet
Douglas MacKinnon was a radio program director, businessman, and music aficionado. The collection includes materials from MacKinnon's many ventures in music and radio, including his work at Harvard University, his leadership at the WQXR radio station in New York, his service in the U.S. Army during World War II, his work with Radio Free Europe, his writings for Opera News, and numerous other interests and pursuits. Also present are MacKinnon's diaries, datebooks, personal correspondence, and autobiographical writings.
10500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Douglas MacKinnon Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1987.
Biographical Note
Douglas MacKinnon studied music at Harvard University. He was musical founder and director of New York's music station WQXR. As assistant to the National Broadcasting Company's Music Counsel, Dr. Walter Damrosch, he helped produce The Children's Hour, did research for the NBC Symphony, and wrote its scripts. In World War II he was a founder of the Armed Forces Master Records (AFMR) which sent disks of classical music to military bases. In the South Pacific he served with the Office of War Information, broadcasting to troops. He also worked as chief of music production for Radio Free Europe.
Other career ventures later in life included Career Protreptors, a music agency; he also reviewed operas throughout the world for the Metropolitan Opera's magazine, Opera News.
Collection Overview
This collection includes a wide range of materials documenting MacKinnon's many pursuits in radio and music. Collection contains diaries, correspondence, financial papers, photographs, printed materials and news clippings related to MacKinnon's radio broadcasting and business career, as well as his personal life. The collection includes materials from MacKinnon's work for WQXR radio, the Armed Forces Master Records, Radio Free Europe, Investors Overseas Services, and Career Protreptors. Also included are notes, ephemera, programs, and his personal critiques of operas he saw around the world; drafts and notes about his autobiography; an assortment of writings and article drafts; photographs from his World War II service; personal documents; extensive correspondence; and other miscellaneous items.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Music and the war; Music -- History and criticism; MacKinnon, Douglas, 1903-1984; MacKinnon, Douglas, 1903-1984; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.); Radio Free Europe; United States. Army; WQXR (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
- Autobiographical Files and Diaries, 1917-1980s and undated; 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of this series consists of MacKinnon's diaries, which range in format from loose typescript pages to small bound manuscript volumes. This series also includes MacKinnon's drafts, research, and notes regarding his autobiography, which he never published.
  - Personal Files, Research, and Drafts of Autobiographies
    - Early schoolwork, 1917 and undated (Box 1)
    - Programs and invitations for performances and life events, 1918-1930s and undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings about MacKinnon, 1940s-1970s (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous: baby hair, photographs, advertisements, undated (Box 1)
    - Materials re: MacKinnon's amphibious Jeep, "Duck", 1948 (Box 1)
    - Career sketches, undated (Box 1)
    - Autobiography drafts and notes, 1950s-1970s and undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Research and correspondence re: funding autobiography, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs (snapshots), 1920s-1960s (Box 20)
      Scope and Contents
      Box 20 includes loose snapshots of MacKinnon's life, including army service, European travel, his youth and college years, and formal portraits. Many of the photographs do not have captioned and have not been arranged beyond being sleeved for preservation.
    - Guestbook, 1916-1920 (Box 21)
    - The University Double Quartet, Harvard University, 1926-1933 and undated; 5 folders (Box 21)
      Includes programs, advertisements, and other publicity materials from MacKinnon's time as manager of the campus group.
    - Financial ledger, 1929-1930 (Box 21)
    - Documents re: vehicles, transportation during cancer treatment, 1980s (Box 16)
    - Ephemera, 1945-1980 and undated (Box 16)
    - Post card album, 1900s (Box 16)
    - Programs/ephemera featuring Douglas MacKinnon as performer, 1923-1930 (Box 16)
    - Programs/ephemera attended by Douglas MacKinnon, 1920s-1970s (Box 16)
    - Financial documents, 1940s-1980s (Box 16)
  - Diaries, 1930s-1980s
    - Miscellaneous diary pages and notes, 1930s-1960s (Box 15)
    - European diary, 1930 (Box 15)
    - Diary, 1933 (Box 15)
    - Food diary, 1934-1935 (Box 15)
    - Europe diary, 1954-1956 (Box 15)
    - Diary and to-do lists, 1956 Apr. (Box 15)
    - Diary: Trip to Spain and Yugoslavia, 1965 July-Aug. (Box 15)
    - Travel diary pages, 1967-1971 (Box 15)
    - Diary, 1971-1973 (Box 15)
    - Diary pages, 1975 (Box 15)
    - Diary pages, 1980 Feb.-May; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Diary pages, 1980 Jun.-Nov. (Box 15)
    - Diary, 1981 June-July (Box 15)
    - Diaries (bound volumes), 1916-1980s (Box 17)
    - Diaries (bound volumes), 1916-1980s (Box 19)
- Writings, 1940s-1980s and undated
  - Le Paquet au Front (address at World Theatre), 1940 Feb 26 (Box 5)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1942, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Song of Faith, by MacKinnon, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Notes and corrections on WQXR article, 1979 and undated (Box 5)
  - Opera News drafts, correspondence, 1958-1981 (Box 5)
  - Articles about opera, 1964-1969 (Box 5)
  - Work for the Geneva Weekly Tribune, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Prisoner in the Congo drafts and article, 1960-1980s (Box 5)
  - Beecham drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - MacKinnon's notes about Rebel in Radio, by Elliott Sanger, along with DM's copy of the book, 1973 and undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and essays, undated (Box 5)
  - Ideas and notes for articles to develop, undated (Box 16)
  - Research notes, undated (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 16)
- Name Files, 2 boxes
  Includes files with MacKinnon's correspondence and collectibles from his relationships with various musicians, public figures, and organizations. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bartok, Bela, and Georges Enesco (Box 9)
  - Bastianini, Ettore (Box 9)
  - Bayreuth, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Blair, David (Box 9)
  - Bordeaux (Box 9)
  - Bregenz (Box 9)
  - Flueli-Ranft (Box 9)
  - Jochum, Eugen (Box 9)
  - Garrison (N.Y.) Art Center (Box 9)
  - Havas, K. (Box 9)
  - Melancon, Louis (photographs) (Box 9)
  - National Folk Festival, 1941 (Box 9)
  - Orff, Carl (Box 9)
  - Orr, Janice (Box 9)
  - Ormandy, Eugene (Box 9)
  - Rusch, Cecile (Box 9)
  - de Saram, Rohan, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Sergio, Lisa (Box 10)
  - Stravinsky, Igor, 1925-1971 (Box 10)
  - Szasz, Tibor (Box 10)
  - Takahara, Memore (Box 10)
  - Vesco, Robert (Box 10)
  - Williams, Ralph Vaughn (Box 10)
  - Yablonskaya, Oxana (Box 10)
  - Zander, Benjamin (Box 10)
- Radio, 1936-1958; 3 boxes
  Photographs, correspondence (including fan mail), scripts, radio programs, press, employment information, and other miscellaneous materials relating to MacKinnon's work at various radio stations. The majority of the series relates to MacKinnon's work as music director for W2XR and WQXR in New York. The series also contains correspondence, notes, and writings by MacKinnon about his employment (and termination) from WXQR in 1941. Other stations represented include Australian Broadcasting Company and WGHF. There is some overlap between this series and the World War II series. Materials from Radio Free Europe are filed under Postwar Employment.
  - Columbia Concerts Corporation, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - W2XR reviews, 1936 (Box 2)
  - WQXR Book-of-the-Month Club concerts, 1939 (Box 2)
  - WQXR Nothing New to Music scripts, 1940 (Box 2)
  - WQXR Nothing New to Music fan mail, 1940 (Box 2)
  - WQXR radio interview transcripts, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - WQXR correspondence, 1937-1941; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs of MacKinnon, undated (Box 2)
  - Medical problems, departure from WQXR, 1941 (Box 2)
  - WQXR correspondence, claims, disputes over employment, 1942-1950s (Box 2)
  - Interstate Broadcasting Company/WQXR copyright disputes (Box 2)
  - WQXR reviews, press, and clippings, 1930s-1970s; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - MacKinnon to Arthur Hays Sulzberger re: WQXR, 1948-1957 (Box 3)
  - WQXR maps and program schedules, undated (Box 3)
  - W2XR and WQXR radio programs, 1936-1942, 1951; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Australian Broadcasting Commission, 1944 (Box 3)
    Transcript, draft, and research for "Lincoln the Man" talk.
  - WHIN Geneva inaugural broadcast transcript, 1947 (Box 3)
  - WGHF radio programs, 1958 (Box 4)
- World War II/Army Life, 1 boxes
  Includes materials from MacKinnon's U.S. Army service during and after World War II. Also includes his work with Armed Forces Master Records, Inc., an organization that distributed music to servicemen.
  - AFMR American Broadcasting in Sydney, Australia, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - AFMR correspondence, 1940s; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - AFMR lists of available music and proposed programs, 1940s (Box 3)
  - Personal military documents and identification cards, 1940s (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous WWII writings and drafts, 1942-1945 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1940s (Box 6)
  - Ephemera, 1940s (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 6)
  - Army printed materials, memos, 1943-1945 (Box 6)
    Includes issues of The Garble, a 5th AACS comedy newsletter.
  - Photographs (snapshots), 1940s (Box 20)
- Correspondence, 1922-1985 and undated; 2 boxes
  Series includes MacKinnon's incoming and outgoing correspondence to a wide range of professional and personal contacts. Arranged in loose chronological order by five-year increments. The remainder of the collection also has correspondence filed with specific events or periods of MacKinnon's life.
  - Correspondence, 1921-1980, 11 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1985 and undated (Box 12)
  - Christmas/New Year's letters to friends and family, 1960s-1980s; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Postcards from MacKinnon to his sister, Mrs. Robert West, 1945-1970 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1954-1973 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence re: autobiography, with Bernice Rodgers, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence kept by DM for autographs (photocopies), 1950s-1980s (Box 12)
- Postwar Employment, 4 boxes
  Includes materials documenting MacKinnon's work with Investors Overseas Services Management (IOS), Career Protreptors, and his financial and other employment records following his work with the U.S. Army. His work with the Metropolitan Opera is documented in the Musical Events series.
  - Radio Free Europe, 3 boxes
    Includes correspondence, scripts, schedules, programming suggestions, publicity, and other materials relating to the operation of Radio Free Europe.
    - Press on RFE, 1951-1956 (Box 7)
    - Editors Bulletin Program Forecast, 1951 Sept.-Dec. (Box 7)
      Issue numbers 10-12, 14-17, 19-20.
    - Editors Bulletin Program Review: Main Polemical Programs, 1952; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Issue numbers 1-9.
    - Listeners Research Bulletin (Czechoslovak desk), 1951 July-Sept. (Box 7)
      Issue numbers 1-2.
    - Scripts for women's programs (English versions for Czechoslovak desk), 1951 (Box 7)
    - Music programs and program preparations, 1951-1952 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous documents and notes, undated (Box 7)
    - Studio schedules, 1951 Apr.-May (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous RFE technical and procedural documents, undated (Box 7)
    - Clippings re: RFE, politics, and culture, 1951-1952; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Radio schedules and programs (all desks: Polish, German, Czech, and Hungarian), 1951-1952 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and interoffice memoranda, 1951 Apr.-1952 May; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Crusade for Freedom materials, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Inaugural broadcast to Czechoslovakia: transcript and press, 1951 May 1 (Box 9)
    - Inaugural broadcast to Hungary: transcript and press, 1951 Oct. 6 (Box 9)
    - Inaugural broadcast to Poland: transcript and press, 1952 May 3 (Box 9)
  - European Festivals and Scenic Tours (EF+ST), 1955-1958
    Contains itineraries, administrative materials, hotel and travel plans, and programs from MacKinnon's operation of a tour through Europe's music festivals in summer of 1956 and 1957.
    - Events and performances in Europe: programs, notes, and reviews, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Tour itineraries and documentation, 1955-1957 (Box 22)
    - Itinerary, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Hotel accomodations, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Expenses and receipts, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Travel information, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Transportation, 1956 (Box 22)
    - Festival tickets, 1956-1957 (Box 22)
    - Applicants correspondence, 1956-1957; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Events and performances in Europe: programs, notes, and reviews, 1958 (Box 22)
    - Inquiries, 1958 (Box 22)
  - Investors Overseas Services (IOS)
    MacKinnon worked for IOS while based in Geneva. This subseries documents his work in the financial sector, during which time he traveled widely through Europe attending opera and music performances.
    - Correspondence, research, 1959-1972 (Box 13)
    - Inside IOS: 12 Exciting and Agonizing Years, by MacKinnon, 1973 (Box 13)
    - Case against DM by Swiss Federal Department of Finance and Customs for smuggling a Chrysler, 1968 (Box 13)
    - IOS reports, 1969-1972 (Box 13)
    - IOS termination correspondence, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Career Protreptors
    MacKinnon operated Career Protreptors, a music representation agency, for a short period of time. The subseries includes drafts and early documentation of the agency, as well as ephemeral materials from some of his clients.
    - Annexes, promotional material, notes, etc., 1972-1981 and undated (Box 13)
    - IRS forms, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Miriam Burton account, 1970s (Box 13)
    - Miriam de Saram corespondence, 1970s (Box 13)
    - Simon Rattle account, 1980 (Box 14)
    - Kronos String Quartet account, 1980-1982 (Box 14)
    - Musical talent research/notes, 1980s (Box 14)
    - Founding, philosophy, introduction to CP, 1967-1982 and undated (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1973, 1981 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, promotional materials, and notes, 1970s-1980s (Box 14)
  - Other Employment
    - Agent for Balazs Nadas, 1946, 1956 (Box 14)
    - Star Broadcasting Company, 1947 (Box 14)
    - Events and performances in Europe: programs, notes, and reviews, 1958; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous professional endeavors: tour guide, lecturer, etc. (Box 15)
- Operas, 1950s-1970s
  MacKinnon's notes, programs, ticket stubs, and other ephemera from his travels to various musical events, largely operas in European cities. Files are arranged by location, either city or country, and often include MacKinnon's handwritten notes about particular operas or performances he attended. Some of these files include his drafts for Opera News articles. Some files also include MacKinnon's press copies of opera performances or theaters, usually intended for circulation and labeled with his name.
  - Douglas MacKinnon's schedules of European opera performances, 1963-1965 (Box 23)
  - Athens, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Baden Baden, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Basel, 1966 (Box 23)
  - Bergen, 1954-1972 (Box 23)
  - Berlin, 1959, 1972 (Box 23)
  - Bern, 1964-1966 (Box 23)
  - Bielefeld, 1961 (Box 23)
  - Brno, 1965 (Box 23)
  - Darmstadt, 1962 (Box 23)
  - Denmark, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Florence, 1964 (Box 23)
  - Freibourg, 1964 (Box 23)
  - Geneva, 1960s-1971; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Great Britain, 1960-1970 (Box 23)
  - Helsinki, 1954-1970 (Box 23)
  - Karlsruhe, 1963 (Box 23)
  - Lausanne, 1961-1965 (Box 23)
  - Lisbon, 1960 (Box 24)
  - Lyon, 1964-1970 (Box 24)
  - Marseille, 1964 (Box 24)
  - Milan, 1962, 1967 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous opera notes, 1959-1968 (Box 24)
  - Montreal Festival, 1941 (Box 24)
  - Montreux, 1968-1970 (Box 24)
  - Munich, 1961-1963 (Box 24)
  - New York City, 1958-1967; 3 folders (Box 24)
    Includes two folders about the Metropolitan Opera House.
  - Paris, 1952-1971 (Box 24)
  - Prague, 1963-1964 (Box 18)
  - Salzburg, 1964-1970 (Box 18)
  - Schwetzingen, 1967 (Box 18)
  - South Africa, 1956-1961 (Box 18)
  - Stockholm, 1962 (Box 18)
  - Stuttgart, 1961 (Box 18)
  - Trieste, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Venice, 1959-1966 (Box 18)
  - Verona, 1963-1966 (Box 18)
  - Vienna, 1955-1970 (Box 18)
  - Wiesbaden, 1963-1970 (Box 18)
  - Yugoslavia, 1959-1960 (Box 18)
  - Zurich, 1959-1968 (Box 18)